<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great danger and uncertainty of death-bed repentance as it was deliver'd in a funeral sermon preach'd lately in the parish-church of Chiswick in Middlesex.</title>
            <author>Ellesby, James, b. 1644 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24951</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08703664</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08703664</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1258:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great danger and uncertainty of death-bed repentance as it was deliver'd in a funeral sermon preach'd lately in the parish-church of Chiswick in Middlesex.</title>
                  <author>Ellesby, James, b. 1644 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Crooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published chiefly for the sake of the ordinary sort of inhabitants of that parish."</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: J. Ellesby.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:41585:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. Lancaſter, <hi>R.P.D.</hi> Hen. Ep. Lond. a Sacris Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 27. 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41585:1"/>
            <p>THE GREAT DANGER AND UNCERTAINTY OF A <hi>Death-Bed Repentance,</hi> As it was Deliver'd in a Funeral Sermon Preach'd lately in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>CHISWICK,</hi> in <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Humble thy ſelf before thou be Sick; and in the time of Sins, ſhew Repentance, <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 18.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>When a Wicked Man Dies, his Expectation ſhall periſh; and the Hope of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Men periſheth, <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 11.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed chiefly for the ſake of the ordinary ſort of Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of that Pariſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41585:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41585:2"/>
            <head>To the Inhabitants of the PARISH of <hi>CHISWICK</hi> in the County of <hi>MIDDLESEX.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH formerly hath been, and in ſome meaſure ſtill is, that great Weakneſs and Indiſpoſition of Body, under which I have labour'd, that I have not been able to go through with my Duty with that Vigour and Conſtancy, as a better meaſure of Health would have enabled me to have done: In particular, my Weakneſs hath diſabled me from making thoſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Viſits to my Neighbours, by going from houſe to houſe, (as I thought my ſelf oblig'd) to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Ignorant, Warn the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly, Reruke the Obſtinate and Profane, and to ſtir up all ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Practice of their Duty, and Amendment of their Lives, where there ſhould be moſt need or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for in: Neither, it may be, would the Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the times, or the Humour of the Age, be able to bear it, had ſuch a thing been undertaken by me; becauſe I find Good Counſel and Advice are very <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwelcome to the Generality of Mankind; and they
<pb facs="tcp:41585:3"/>who ſtand in moſt need of Admonition and Reproof, are commonly the greateſt <hi>Deſpiſers</hi> of it. For ſuch Fools <hi>as make a Mock of Sin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9, 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.7, 22, 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.12.</note> uſually make a ſcorn of Reproof too, and thereby give but ſmall Hopes of their ever being Reclaim'd, or Growing better, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot but render their Condition ſo much the more Deſperate. For the Wiſe Man hath aſſured us, Prov. <hi>15.10. He that hateth Reproof ſhall Die.</hi> And, <hi>Eccleſ. 21.6. He that hateth to be Reprov'd is in the way of Sinners,</hi> that is, in the High way to Ruin and Deſtruction, as all Wicked Men are, who ſtop their Ears againſt Inſtruction and Reproof.</p>
            <p>And tho' I have not been backward in Publick to warn all ſuch among you of their Great Guilt and Danger on that account; yet there are many of you, who ſeldom or never ſee the inſide of a Church; or if they do, little Regard what is Taught and Learn'd them there, thinking what is deliver'd to All in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, doth not concern themſelves in particular.</p>
            <p>To Supply this Defect on my part, and to Remedy what I can, this great Careleſneſs and Neglect on Yours, I have been prevail'd withal to publiſh the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe, which was lately Preach'd on a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Occaſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41585:3"/>
            <p>I have propos'd the Example of the Deceaſed, as a Sea-mark to Caution you againſt thoſe dangerous Rocks and Shelves, which he run himſelf upon; the ill Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whereof he Complain'd of and Lamented with his lateſt Breath. And this I have done in as favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a manner as I could, or was Conſiſtent with the nature of my Deſign, which was to Inſtruct and Warn the Living, without bearing hard on the Memory of the Dead, who is now paſs'd from Man's Judgment-Seat to that of God's: Therefore I have not mention'd any thing of the Name or Circumſtances of the Deceaſed Party, whereby he might be known to thoſe that knew him not before; and have confin'd my ſelf to his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in his Sickneſs, and what he was pleas'd to take notice of publickly to other People, rather than to my ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Duty I here perſwade you to is One of the moſt Neceſſary and Important in all Religion; and indeed Comprehenſive of all others: For True Repentance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in a confeſſing our ſelves to be Sinners in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; or in being Troubled for our Sins, and Begging Pardon for them when we can Sin no longer. This is no other than groſs Deluſion and Hypocriſie: 'Tis one of the <hi>Snares of the Devil,</hi> which he lays for the Ruin of Souls; but Repentance conſiſts in a Hating and Forſaking of all Sin, in the Watching of your
<pb facs="tcp:41585:4"/>Hearts, and Bridling of your Tongues, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining of your Paſſions, and Mortifying the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Luſts of the Fleſh, and in Arming your ſelves againſt all thoſe Sins and Temptations, which you are Prone to Offend in, and have formerly been overcome by.</p>
            <p>This is the True Notion of Evangelical Saving Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to which the Promiſes of the Goſpel are made, and upon which <hi>alone</hi> we can give you any Comfortable Hopes of Pardon and Forgiveneſs at the hands of God, either <hi>Now,</hi> or when you come to <hi>Die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray God ſet theſe great Truths home upon your Hearts and Conſciences; that in this your Day you may <hi>ſee the things that belong to your Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are hid from your Eyes.</hi> So prays He that unfeignedly Wiſhes the Eternal Happineſs and Salvation of you all, and who is deſirous to Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, (as his Duty obligeth him) what ever lies in his Power toward it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Ellesby.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 28th, 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41585:4"/>
            <head>THE Great Danger and Uncertainty Of a <hi>Death-Bed Repentance.</hi> As it was Deliver'd in a Funeral Sermon Preach'd lately in the Pariſh Church of <hi>CHISWICK.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hebr. III. 7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Wherefore, as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if you will hear his Voice, Harden not your Hearts, as in the Provocation, in the Day of Temptation, in the Wilderneſs.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE things which accompany Salvation and relate to the Happineſs of a Future State, are of that infinite Moment and Concern to every Man living, and the Time allotted by God for the Diſcharge and Performance of them, ſo ſhort and uncertain, that we ought to let ſlip no Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for to admoniſh and put you in Mind thereof. We cannot too earneſtly preſs and perſuade you thereunto on the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41585:5"/>one Hand; neither on the other, can you be too diligent and ſerious in a matter of that vaſt Importance, whereon endleſs Bliſs or Woe, eternal Happineſs or Miſery, do moſt aſſuredly depend.</p>
            <p>This is that which we ought to make the main Buſineſs of our Lives, as ſoon as ever we arrive to years of Knowledge and Underſtanding, and are able to diſcern the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Evil; for, ſet aſide the proſpect of Happineſs in <hi>another</hi> State, whereof we are but Candidates and Probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in <hi>this,</hi> and the preſent Life would not be very deſireable for its own ſake; neither ſhould we have any great Reaſon to be fond of it; for the many Troubles and Calamities we daily meet withall in the World, would embitter Life to that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as to make us Diſreliſh all the Comforts and Enjoyments thereof. The Hopes therefore of a future Recompence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, of <hi>a more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory,</hi> is the greateſt Anchour to ſupport the Spirits of good Men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bear up their Minds, amidſt all the Storms of an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and Calamitous Eſtate.</p>
            <p>But alaſs! Unleſs our Hopes of Happineſs are firmly ſettled and well grounded, they will moſt certainly deceive and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point us in the end; for 'tis only Repentance for Sin paſt, and a Life of Holineſs and new Obedience for time to come, that can give us good Hope through Grace, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.16. <hi>And make us Partakers of that Glory which hereafter ſhall be Revealed,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>They are ſuch only, who truly Believe, Repent, and obey the Goſpel, and ſpend ſome conſiderable part of their Lives in ſo doing, that can have any ſolid Hopes or Comfortable expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their future Safety and well being; whereas the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Hopes of bad Men and preſuming Sinners, which <hi>Job calls the hope of the Hypocrite ſhall periſh, and like a Spiders Web deceive thoſe that ſhall truſt to it,</hi> Job 8.13.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41585:5"/>
            <p>But now to come more cloſely to the matter in Hand: If we would have our Repentance to be Repentance unto Life, or ſuch as will entitle us to the Pardon of our Sins, and acceptance with God, we muſt take the Holy Ghoſt's advice in the Text, <hi>not to harden our Hearts,</hi> nor ſtop our Ears againſt his Calls and Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to this Duty, but we muſt ſet about it preſently, <hi>to day while it is called to day,</hi> v. 13. becauſe to morrow 'tis poſſible may be <hi>too late.</hi> We muſt reſolve to Repent immediately and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, before we have provok'd God too far, or tempted him to give us up, as he hath done many others, to a hardned and impenitent Eſtate; for 'tis poſſible a Man may outlive the Seaſons of Grace, and Sin away the acceptable Time and Day of Salvation; he may ſink and plunge himſelf ſo far into that depth of Guilt and Wickedneſs, by adding one Sin and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to another, as it will be ſcarce poſſible to recover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the Snare of the Devil, or to free himſelf from the gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity, be ſure not without a great deal of Trouble and Difficulty, nor till after a long time ſpent in deep Sorrow and Contrition, and in the painful acts of Mortification and Self-Denial.</p>
            <p>The time paſt can never be recall'd, and time to come is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uncertain, the preſent time is only ours, and what we can be moſt ſure of; and therefore we ſhould be careful not to let it ſlip from us without improving it to the great ends and Purpoſes of Religion, to the reconciling our Selves to God, perfecting the work of Repentance, and <hi>giving all Diligence to make our calling and Election ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which purpoſe I ſhall apply this Advice which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> gives us in the Text, <hi>To day if you will hear his Voice harden not your Hearts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The words contain,</p>
            <p>Firſt, An Exhortation to Belief, as appears by the Context, expreſt here by Hearing or Harkning to the Voice of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A diſſwaſion from Impenitency or Hardning our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41585:6"/>Hearts through Unbelief, both which are in the third place, reinforc'd by the Authority of the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation this is, <hi>Wherefore, as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if you will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which words I ſhall diſcourſe unto you on the Three following Particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Unbelief is one great Cauſe of Impenitency or Hardneſs of Heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That Impenitency or Hardneſs of Heart is a Sin very provoking of God, and admits of great Aggravations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall endeavour to diſſwade from this Sin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce the Exhortation of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> by laying before you the great and abſolute neceſſity of Repentance, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the preſent Time in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Unbelief is one great Cauſe of Impenitency, and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart. Infidelity hath been judg'd the root of all Sin, eſpecially in Chriſtians, for did they really and heartily believe the great and important Truth of that Religion they make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of, wherein the motives and arguments to a good Life are ſo very ſtrong and powerfull, and the threats and diſſwaſives from Sin and Vice are ſo convincing and amazing, 'tis ſcarce poſſible they ſhould allow themſelves in thoſe Vile and Sinful courſes which are ſo riſe among Chriſtians, or give ſuch ſmall hopes of their Repentance, as many do.</p>
            <p>Did they believe in good earneſt, there was a God, a God of that infinite Power and Purity, hating of all Sin, and threatning to puniſh it in the moſt ſevere and terrible manner, they would not dare to affront him, and fly in his Face with their horrid Oaths and Curſes, Blaſphemies and Imprecations, as frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they do; they would not live <hi>without God in the World,</hi> nor caſt off all Fear and Reverence to his Holy Name and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Laws. Did they believe in Chriſt, as the Son of God and Saviour of the World, they would not, with the Jews murder
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41585:6"/>and <hi>crucifie him afreſh</hi> by their oft repeated Sins and Impieties, nor <hi>do deſpite to the Spirit of Grace,</hi> by quenching his holy Motions, or reſiſting the checks of their own Conſcience. Did they believe a future Judgment and Life to come, they would ſtand in greater awe thereof, and be afraid to provoke him, that will be their Judge, and call them to a ſtrict account, for all the Actions of their Lives paſt, for all the neglects of his Grace, contempt of his Mercy, and Defiance of his Judgment; they would not then increaſe their Accounts, nor ſwell them up into ſuch a frightful Maſs of Guilt, as will make them one day ſtand amaz'd at the Sight thereof. Did they believe there was a Heaven for the reward of good Men, and a Hell for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Bad, they durſt not make ſo light of either; but become more Carefull and Sollicitous to ſecure the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the one, and avoid the unſpeakable Torments and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of the other.</p>
            <p>But <hi>all Men have not Faith,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, no, nor all Chriſtians neither; they do not heartily believe what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>for while they profeſs to know God, in their Works they deny him, being abominable, diſobedient, and unto every good work Reprobate. Tit.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>The effect commonly points out the Cauſe, and the Action uſually diſcovers the Principle from whence it flows: and if ſo, we may juſtly ſuſpect the greateſt part of the Chriſtian World, to be void of that Faith they make Profeſſion of, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as little of their Religion as they practiſe of it. Their Lives and Actions beſpeak many of them to be rather Atheiſts than Chriſtians, and downright Infidels than true Believers, for true Faith, or the through Belief of the Doctrine of Chriſt, would influence their Lives in another guiſe manner, than what is commonly obſerved in the World; it would make them live better, be more ſhy of Sin, and cautious of offending; if therefore Men would examine their Hearts and Souls, or ſearch into the Root and bottom of their Actions, they would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41585:7"/>find a great deal of Infidelity or Unbelief to lurk there, and that Chriſt among all his Nominal Profeſſors and Diſciples hath but a ſmall number of thoſe that believe in him aright; or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <hi>to the Reuelation which God hath given us of his Son,</hi> as long therefore as they have an <hi>evil Heart of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief it will make them to depart from the living God,</hi> Heb. 3.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This Impenitency and Hardneſs, which is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by Unbelief, is very provoking to God, and admits of very great Aggravations under the Goſpel, becauſe thereby Men ſhut their Eyes againſt the cleareſt and moſt manifeſt Light, and harden their Hearts againſt the moſt importunate Calls and Invitation to Repentance. <hi>The former times of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance God winked at,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. that is, God was willing to paſs by and overlook in agreat Meaſure, the Ignorance and Impenitence of the Heathen World in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of what he doth now under the Goſpel, <hi>by which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all men every where to repent;</hi> ſo that Repentance is become a more expreſs Command, and ſtrictly enjoyn'd Duty, now than formerly; and therefore Impenitency is a Sin much more inexcuſable and provoking in Chriſtians than it was in Heathens, conſidering what Means and Motives the Goſpel affords to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, What helps and aſſiſtances it doth offer towards their Converſion and Amendment, which the World was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made acquainted with before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God who at ſundry times and in diverſe manners, ſpake in times paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets; hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken to us by his Son, &amp;c. Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. Him hath he ſent as a Phyſician to call and invite you to Repentance, and through him forgiveneſs is preach'd and promis'd to all that in good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arneſt repent of their Sins, and endeavour to amend and live better for time to come. Acts 5.31. <hi>Him hath God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halted with his right Hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, for to give Repentance to Iſrael, and Forgiveneſs of Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, the drawing us to Repentance, in order to our Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41585:7"/>is the main Purpoſe and Deſign of the Goſpel, and of all its Precepts and Commands, Threats and Promiſes. Now for any Man who believes the Goſpel, and underſtands the end and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign thereof, to ſtop his Ears againſt ſo many gracious Calls and Invitations, to harden his Heart againſt ſo much Love and Goodneſs, to remain ſtupid and inſenſible under ſo many pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Motives and Inducements as the Goſpel affords him in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his Repentance muſt needs be a high Aggravation of his Guilt, and mighty Provocation to God. It provok'd him ſo far againſt the Iſraelites, <hi>that he ſwore in his Wrath, they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into his Reſt,</hi> Heb. 3.11.</p>
            <p>Impenitency therefore hath been always look'd upon as a very great and dangerous Sin, inſomuch as ſome have thought it to be the <hi>Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> of which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>it ſhall never be forgiven, either in this World, or in the World to come,</hi> Matth. 12.32. But however 'tis acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all to be equally fatal and dangerous to the Souls of Men, for no Sin ſhall be pardoned unleſs it be throughly repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and the longer any Man continues in a ſinful State, the leſs hopes he gives of his Repentance every day than other, and conſequently the further off from the hopes of Pardon.</p>
            <p>To be ſometimes overtaken with a Fault, or ſurpriz'd againſt our Wills by a Temptation, is the Frailty and Infirmity of humane Nature, and may draw forth pity in God as well as Man, but wilfully to run or fall into a Sin, and when we are once fallen, to lie and wallow in it, as Swine do in the Mire; when we have done amiſs not to be ſorry for it, but to laugh at good Counſel and Advice, or fly in the Face of thoſe that ſhall admoniſh and reprove us for our Faults, this is that which ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravates a Crime, and adds mightily to the Guilt of it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Sin becomes as the Apoſtle doth expreſs it, <hi>exceeding</hi> or <hi>out of Meaſure Sinful.</hi> This is that which provokes the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſtirs up his Anger and Diſpleaſure againſt his Creatures; this makes him to whet his Sword, and bend his Bow, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41585:8"/>in readineſs the Inſtruments of Death. Had <hi>Judas</hi> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted throughly and in good earneſt, we have reaſon to think his Condition had been leſs deſperate; for the ſame moſt precious Bloud of the Crucified Jeſus, was able to atone for <hi>his</hi> Guilt that betray'd him, as well as for <hi>theirs,</hi> that murder'd and put him to Death; but we read of the Repentance of the one, and not of the other, or if he repented, it was without hopes of Pardon and purpoſe of Amendment, which therefore ended in Death.</p>
            <p>Chriſt dyed for all, but only the Impenitent, for no Sin in it ſelf is too great for Pardon, if repented off and forſaken in time; but 'tis impenitency which puts Venom into every Sin, and makes the Sting ſo deadly and Mortal, and binds us over to everlaſting Puniſhment, <hi>for except ye repent, ye ſhall all Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> ſaith our Saviour. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3. and again, <hi>Repent and be converted, that your Sins may be blotted out,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Acts 3.19.</p>
            <p>Implying that they that do not Repent, ſhall certainly Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and no hopes to have our Sins Pardon'd and blotted out, unleſs we actually turn from them and forſake them in time. In a word. Repentance is all along in the Goſpel, made the chief condition of Forgiveneſs, without which no Sin can be Remitted, no hopes of Salvation given to the Sinner, whether living or dying.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let me in the next place diſſwade you from this great Sin of <hi>Impenitency</hi> and <hi>Hardneſs</hi> of <hi>Heart,</hi> and thereby reinforce the exhortation of the Holy Ghoſt in the Text; by ſhewing you the great and abſolute neceſſity of a Timely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or of redeeming the preſent time to that purpoſe, and my requeſt is, that every one that reads this, would apply it home to his own Soul and Conſcience, and make a particular Application thereof for his own Uſe and Benefit, in as ſerious a manner, as if God himſelf ſhould addreſs to him by Name, as he did to <hi>Job,</hi> out of the <hi>Whirlwind,</hi> Job 38.1. or as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41585:8"/>Chriſt did to <hi>Saul</hi> upon his Journey to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> Acts, 9.4. For the exhortation is the Holy Ghoſt's, and therefore to be lookt upon as the Advice of God rather than Man.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Now my Advice in Conjunction with that of the Holy Ghoſt's in the Text is this; That you would no longer ſtop your Ears nor harden your Hearts againſt the Calls of God, or Voice of his Miniſters, when they exhort you to repent and turn from the evil of your ways, and to amend the wickedneſs of your Lives; but that you would find ſome time to bethink your Selves of your Spiritual Eſtate in order to that which is Eternal, and to ſecure the intereſt of your immortal Souls, by making a timely proviſion for them; which can be done no other way than by ſetting about the great and neceſſary work of Repentance and good Living, which through Faith in the Merits of your Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Redeemer, is the only thing that can ſecure the endleſs Happineſs of another World, when you leave this.</p>
            <p>And be ſure you endeavour it forthwith and out of Hand, even <hi>to Day, while it is call'd to Day;</hi> do it in the time of your Health and Strength, while the moſt Merciful God doth afford you Time and Space to repent and amend your Lives in, which you cannot hope to do, when Death begins to Approach, Strength to Fail, and Life it ſelf is ready to expire.</p>
            <p>'Tis my Duty to take all Occaſions to remind you thereof, both <hi>in Seaſon and out of Seaſon,</hi> and therefore I was willing to lay hold of this, to ſtir you up to a ſerious and due regard of the great intereſt of your Souls, before it be too late, and 'tis your Duty to <hi>receive the Truth in the Love</hi> thereof, and follow that Counſel and Advice which is intended for your Good, and will put you into a ſafe and happy Condition, both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>And let me add one thing farther, That Perſons of all Ages and Degrees are concern'd in this Admonition, and 'tis their Intereſt to attend and become obedient thereunto.</p>
            <p>Young People ought as the Wiſe Man exhorts them, <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their Creator in the days of their Touth,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41585:9"/>and endeavour to be good betimes, becauſe their Life is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain as that of others; for more die <hi>young</hi> than live to be <hi>old,</hi> and being once arriv'd to years of Knowledge and Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they have an account to give to God as well as older Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and conſequently are capable of being Happy or Miſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble for Ever.</p>
            <p>Elder People ought to ſet about the amending and reforming of their Lives in time of their Health and Strength, while they may moſt conveniently do it, as being endu'd with Ripeneſs of Judgment and Underſtanding, and in ſome Meaſure paſt the Follies and Vanities of Youth; 'tis time therefore for them to grow ſerious and act like Men and Women in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giou's as well as Worldly concerns.</p>
            <p>Ancient People more eſpecially ought to do this, before Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Death doth ſieze them, as having neglected it too long already, and therefore have leſs time to do it in, than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they had. It concerns them then to be careful to lay hold of the preſent Opportunity while it is yet before them; for if you that are ancient and travelling apace to your Grave, will not grow ſerious and make proviſion for Eternity, when, O when! will you do it; you are already arrived at the 11th. hour of the day, have a care of deferring it to the 12th and laſt, when the dark night of Death is ready to overtake you, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>no Man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more: To this Duty of a timely and undelay'd Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the Rich Man and Man of Honour is oblig'd as well as the Poor and mean Man for as their Talents are more; ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Accounts will be greater than that of their Inferiours; and what through the ſnares of the World and Temptations of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, they are in a great deal more danger to Periſh and miſcarry; whereupon the Salvation of Rich and Great Men ſeems by that of our Saviour to be abundance more hard and difficult, than that of other Men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.23. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, a rich Man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41585:9"/>
            <p>The number of the <hi>Saved</hi> in general is like to be but few and ſmall, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.14. and <hi>c.</hi> 22.14. but be ſure that of Rich Men will be the leaſt and feweſt of all others, becauſe <hi>not many mighty, not many noble are called,</hi> 1. Cor. 1.26. and therefore it concerns them chiefly to watch and pray againſt thoſe many great Temptations, which a Rich and Proſperous Eſtate is wont to expoſe and lay them open to, and to <hi>work out their Salvation with Fear and Trembling,</hi> becauſe of the difficulty thereof, and to take time enough before hand, for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Repentance delay'd and put off <hi>from the preſent time to the Future,</hi> is matter of great Hazard and Uncertainty, and 'tis mighty odds, if ever ſuch a one doth repent at all.</p>
            <p>A dying Bed proves commonly too late, and very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for this great and neceſſary Duty. Times of Sickneſs and Weakneſs are uſually taken up with other guiſe concerns, and attended with many inconvenient Circumſtances, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Repentance very difficult at ſuch a time, and at the beſt but doubtful and uncertain.</p>
            <p>Now the difficulties of ſuch a Repentance may ariſe, either, <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the Violence or Malignity of the Diſeaſe, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly may be of that nature as to ſieze the Head, ſtupifie the Brain, and take away the uſe of the Senſes and Underſtanding, without which no Man is or can be capable of the <hi>leaſt act</hi> of Repentance, nor of doing any thing towards it; and in ſuch a Caſe to repent is plainly impoſſible. But, 2. the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Duty ariſe moſt commonly from the nature of ill Habits and bad Cuſtoms, which are not eaſily broken, or left off on a Sudden, nor yet new ones immediately planted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd in the room thereof; for all Habits are produc'd by Acts, and therefore muſt be weakned by degrees, and worn out by their Contraries, for which Reaſon 'tis neceſſary that we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom our ſelves to frequent Acts of Vertue, to wear out the Habits of Vice; but then this requires conſtant Uſe and Practice, and ſome conſiderable length of Time for that Purpoſe, both
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41585:10"/>which are commonly wanting, to thoſe that are Sick and Weak, and more eſpecially when they are Dying.</p>
            <p>But to make the beſt of their Caſe, ſuppoſe they ſhould be willing to ſet about the Duty of repenting before they Die, and may be judg'd able to do ſomething towards it, ſomething like it at ſuch a time; yet no Man living can judge of the Truth and Sincerity of ſuch a Repentance, much leſs give the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> any great Hopes of Comfort thereupon. I am ſure we have no warrant from God ſo to do, there is no promiſe made to ſuch late and dying Penitents. And to give them any hopes of Pardon without a Promiſe to ground ſuch hopes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is not to comfort but flatter the Souls of Men, and deceive them to their utter Ruine and Diſappointment in the end.</p>
            <p>For to give wicked Men at their Deaths any Hopes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is to give the <hi>Childrens Bread to Dogs,</hi> and proſtitute the precious promiſes of the Goſpel to the encouragement of Sin and Vice, which is wholly contrary to the deſign thereof.</p>
            <p>Moreover we have a great deal more Reaſon to ſuſpect than hope well of ſuch Mens Repentance, becauſe we often find a great deal of Deceitfulneſs and Hypocriſie in the moſt ſolemn profeſſion of Grief and Sorrow, in the moſt ſerious and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Promiſes of Amendment, that have been made by ſick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, when under the apprehenſions of Death, and the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of an awakned Conſcience; for 'tis uſual for ſuch Penitents upon their Recovery, to forget all that ever they Promiſed to Almighty God, and to grow rather worſe than better. We meet with too many inſtances daily for to confirm us in the belief of this Truth, and I am ſorry to think that there ſhould be any among you of this Pariſh to make up the Number; ſome of whom I have viſited in their Sickneſs, been witneſs to their Vows and Promiſes ſolemnly made to God of new and better Obedience, who yet have <hi>ſtarted aſide like a broken Bow,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved themſelves falſly in</hi> God's <hi>Covenant,</hi> Pſalm 78.37, 57.</p>
            <p>Such I do earneſtly deſire, and in the name of God ſeriouſly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41585:10"/>charge <hi>to remember from whence they are fallen,</hi> to call to mind the many Vows and Promiſes made to God in the time of their Trouble and Diſtreſs, and to make Conſcience of the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof, as conſidering that the <hi>bitterneſs of Death</hi> is not yet paſt, and they know not how ſoon God may reduce them to the like or worſe Circumſtances, lay his Hand more heavy upon them, and fill their Souls with far greater Horrour and Amazement in the remembrance of their <hi>Vile Hypocriſie,</hi> and <hi>abominable Diſſimulation:</hi> And how then can they hope, God ſhould hear their Cries and accept their Vows, who have been already ſo falſe and treacherous to their Word and Promiſe; the <hi>laſt Eſtate</hi> of ſuch Men and Women, 'tis to be fear'd, <hi>will be worſe than their Firſt,</hi> Luke 11.26.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider further, you that are apt to put off the thoughts of Death, and of Repentance with it, if you cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſerious thoughts of dying now, how will you be able to bear up under the near Approaches and feeling Apprehenſions thereof, when Death ſhall overtake and ſieze you in good earneſt, and there ſhall be no hopes to eſcape or avoid it, what, Oh! what will you then do?</p>
            <p>The Apprehenſions of Death to a ſick Man are very Awful and Terrible, but much more ſo to one that finds himſelf unprovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for it, to one that is unfit to give up his accounts to God, or appear with Comfort before his Great and Dreadful Tribunal.</p>
            <p>If the great and neceſſary duties of Repentance and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Mortification and Self denial be judg'd ſo hard and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to you now, do you think the Trouble and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof will wear off and grow leſs by your delays, or ſhall you be better able to maſter or overcome them, when you ſhall want both Time and Strength to go through with them.</p>
            <p>He that thinks ſeriouſly of Death and a future Judgment to enſue thereupon, methinks cannot be ſo much forſaken of his own Senſe and Reaſon, as not to judge it neceſſary to make the beſt and moſt timely preparation for them that he can, and to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41585:11"/>uſe all the helps and aſſiſtances of Religion for that end and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For God's Sake, Sirs, conſider of theſe things in time, and bethink your Selves in good earneſt before the <hi>Evil days come, and the Years draw nigh, wherein you ſhall ſay, I have no pleaſure in them.</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1. and let the Advice of the Holy Ghoſt in the Text prevail with you, though mine cannot. <hi>To day, if you will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember your immortal Souls are in danger every hour, every Moment that you live in any known wilful Sin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to repent of it: Life is ſhort, frail, and uncertain, Eternity is at Hand and haſtens upon you apace; Heaven and Hell are at the end of your Lives, and ſtand ready to receive you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you have fitted and prepared your Selves either for the one or for the other; thoſe Spirits which you carry in your Boſoms muſt live for ever; <hi>for ever,</hi> I ſay, in perpetual Bliſs or endleſs Woe, and we have all but a little time before us to ſecure our Eternal State in, therefore be ſure to find time to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and ſet about it; whatever you neglect, do not neglect the things that belong to your Everlaſting Peace; let not the Cares, the Buſineſs, and the Troubles of the World, much leſs the vain and fooliſh Pleaſures and Paſtimes thereof miſimploy your time, and take you off from this <hi>one thing needful</hi> and moſt neceſſary.</p>
            <p>You that are <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Mean</hi> in the World ought to do this; you ought to find ſome time to make Proviſion for your Souls as well as for your Bodies, and to labour as diligently for the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> as for the <hi>Meat that Periſhes;</hi> for according to the Apoſtle, <hi>Meat is for the Belly, and the Belly for Meat, but God will deſtroy both it and them;</hi> whereas the Bread of Life which comes <hi>down from Heaven</hi> is able to nouriſh your Souls unto Eternal Life, ſo as never to hunger or thirſt more. Alas! What ſignifies it for you to drudge and toyl, and take pains to maintain your Bodies, and in the end to loſe your Souls, for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41585:11"/>want of ſetting apart ſome time, and beſtowing ſome care up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially you that are above the <hi>wants</hi> and <hi>neceſſities</hi> of the World, and have ſo much time and leaſure lying on your Hands, that you complain thereof, and know not well how to get rid of it, or paſs it away, except it be by <hi>Drinking</hi> or <hi>Gaming,</hi> by going to <hi>Plays,</hi> and running into bad <hi>Company</hi> to divert your ſelves; ſuch as you, be ſure, will be <hi>Inexcuſable</hi> before God, if inſtead of laying hold of the preſent Opportunity, to make ready your Accounts againſt the <hi>Judgment of the great Day,</hi> you ſhall ſwell and increaſe them, by a Life of Sloth and Vanity, Luxury and Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>To ſuch as you therefore, I addreſs my ſelf, not as the <hi>Rich</hi> and Great ones of the World, for as ſuch commonly you are apt to <hi>Deſpiſe our Counſel</hi> and think your ſelves <hi>above Reproof;</hi> but as Frail, Dying, Mortal Men, who muſt ſhortly Die as well as others, have your Duſt mingled with that of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and all your Pride and Greatneſs, Niceneſs and Delicacy converted into Stench and Rottenneſs, and the Diſhonours of the Grave; and moreover as having many more Talents to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for, than your Poor and Indigent Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Is not the Day of your Death as certain as that of your Birth or preſent Life; and tho' you are loth to think of Dying, and willing to put off the Evil Day far from you as a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly proſpect, and Unwelcome entertainment; as a Subject that is apt to damp your Mirth, and unſuitable to your brisk and gay humours: Yet conſider the putting off the thoughts of Death will not prevent its Approach, or make it leſs Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible when it comes; nay, quite otherwiſe, it will make the ſurprize thereof more dreadful and amazing, and render you ſo much the more unfit to grapple, and encounter with the <hi>King of Terrours,</hi> Eccleſiaſticus, 41.1. <hi>O Death how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that lives at rest in his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, unto the man that hath nothing to vex him, and that hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41585:12"/>proſperity in all things; yea, unto him that is yet able to receive meat.</hi> The more unwilling you have been to think of, and prepare for Death now, the more aſtoniſhing will the approach of it be then, and fill you with dreadful Agonies and Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Soul beyond what I am able to expreſs, or 'tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for you to conceive at preſent.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the Deſpondencies and Miſgivings of heart, which have ſiez'd Good men at their Death, have been very great and apt to fill them with Fears and Apprehenſions: O how Frightful and Intolerable then muſt thoſe Horrours and Confuſions be, which the Conſciences of wicked men uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally feel at the approach of Death: <hi>Conſcience,</hi> I ſay, when throughly rowz'd and awaken'd in the ſenſe of their former Guilt and approaching Puniſhment: the Anguiſh thereof in ſome Men and Women hath been ſo great that they have thought themſelves in <hi>Hell</hi> already, and that their condition could not well be worſe in the very <hi>Place of Torments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, Sirs, think often, think ſeriouſly of theſe things before hand; call to mind your latter End and prepare for it in <hi>good</hi> earneſt before it comes, and that may be one way to prevent the <hi>bitterneſs</hi> of Death, and take away the Sting of it.</p>
            <p>For without a timely Repentance, and Preparation for it, 'tis not a ſaying, <hi>God be merciful to me a Sinner,</hi> Luk. 13.25. or <hi>Lord, Lord, open unto us,</hi> Matth. 7.21. that will gain us admittance into the Kingdom of Heaven: 'Tis not a little outward Grief, or forc'd Sorrow that can ſupply the want of Repentance, or be accepted by God in the ſtead thereof: No, no, To <hi>Repent</hi> is to be ſo heartily Troubled and Sorry for your Sins, as to grow out of Love with them, and to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve immediately to <hi>Leave</hi> and <hi>Forſake</hi> them; to <hi>Repent</hi> is to <hi>Amend</hi> and <hi>Reform</hi> whatever you ſee amiſs in your ſelves; 'tis to become Wiſer and Better for the future, and to lead your Lives according to the Directions of the Goſpel, and Precepts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41585:12"/>of your moſt Holy Religion: And he that doth not endeavour to do this in good earneſt, knows not what true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance means; he is a ſtranger to the Grace of God, and is not yet arrived to the condition of Life, or terms of Salvation, and conſequently not in a capacity of being ſav'd.</p>
            <p>Now we cannot but think, (and therefore ought to let you know as much) that it will be too late to do this, when you are Sick and Dying; you will want time and opportunity for it, when life is drawing to an end, and Death with all his Terrours and Affrightments is haſtning toward you. O then, what would you give for a little of that Health and Strength which you have formerly miſpent in Sin and Folly, in gratifying the luſts of the Fleſh, in complying with the Pride and Vanity of the World, and running your ſelves into the Snares and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Devil; what would you not do to gain a little more of that time and leaſure to go through with your Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Preparations for Eternity, which you have wretchedly abus'd and thrown away upon your Exceſſes and Debaucheries, upon your Luſts and Pleaſures, in a Vain, Sinful, and Unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner; <hi>what Fruit</hi> will you then <hi>have of thoſe things, whereof you</hi> will be aſham'd? <hi>For the end of thoſe things is Death.</hi> Rom. 6.21.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Then you will ſee, that the leaſt hour of your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent time will be worth more than a whole Age of Folly and Vanity; you will wiſh then (whatever you may think of it now) that the greater Portions of your life had been ſpent in the Cloſet at your Private Prayers, or at Church in the Publick Worſhip and Service of God, or in ſeeking and finding out op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing Good, rather than in Dreſſing and going Fine, in Gaming and Playing, in Idle and Impertinent Viſiſts, in Cenſorious and unprofitable Converſation, which engroſſes ſo much of the time of our People of Quality, both Men and Women, many of whom are mightily guilty this way, and are obſerv'd to ſpend their time the vaineſt of all others: Nay, ſome among them that are pleaſed to take up a ſhew and Profeſſion of Religion, give us too much reaſon to fear, 'tis rather for Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41585:13"/>and Faſhion ſake, than out of Conſcience, becauſe ſo very few are known to become any whit the better or more ſerious upon that account: And for my part, I do not ſee how 'tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to reconcile the ſtrictneſs of Religion and a Holy Life (to which the greateſt ſtand obliged as well as the meaneſt) with thoſe undue Liberties, which our People of Quality do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly take in many things, and particularly in the inſtances before mention'd.</p>
            <p>O my God! What account will they be able to give another day; when all thoſe Helps and Advantages both of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Leaſure, Riches</hi> and <hi>Honour, Interest</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> wherewith they might do a great deal of good to themſelves and others, and become Exemplary to their Inferiours, ſhall yet be abus'd and miſimploy'd in the worſt manner that can be, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come matter of publick Scandal and Offence.</p>
            <p>Is this to anſwer the end of their coming into the World, or the way to prepare themſelves for a happy <hi>Exit</hi> or departure out of it? Is this to live like <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or to ſpend their time like thoſe that muſt be accountable to God for it?</p>
            <p>But Death, when it comes will open their Eyes, though they ſhut them now, and convince them of their errour and miſtake, though we cannot: But then it may be too late and out of their power to retreive or amend it. Remember you can never be too fit to die, nor too careful and ſollicitous in preparing your ſelves for it; becauſe it is a thing that can be done but once, and Eternity depends upon the Well-doing of it.</p>
            <p>He then that ſhall deferr his Preparations for Eternity, till he comes to be ſick unto Death, and ready to go out of the World, hoping that may be time enough for it, will find himſelf very unfit for ſo great a Work, and mightily deceiv'd and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his Hope. For Experience tells us, whatever is done in haſt, is commonly done by halves and hurry'd up in a ſlight and imperfect manner; many things are wont to be forgotten and over lookt at ſuch a time; and therefore the Errours and Miſtakes, the Omiſſions and Overſights of a Repentance hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41585:13"/>up in haſt when we come to die, muſt needs be many and great; the leaſt whereof may prove Fatal and undo us for ever.</p>
            <p>'Tis Wiſdom therefore to ſet about it now, while time and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity are before you; while God offers you his Grace, and ſtretches forth the Arms of his Mercy to welcome and embrace you, as the Father did the <hi>Prodigal Son</hi> upon his Repentance and Return.</p>
            <p>Do it to day, <hi>while it is call'd to day, for you know not what a day may bring forth,</hi> Prov. 27.1. or what danger you may run to all Eternity by the leaſt delay: A day, an hour, nay a few Moments may paſs you out of this life into the <hi>Regions of the ſhadow of Death,</hi> and land you upon the Confines of the other World, and make your condition Deſperate, and for ever Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> To this Duty of the Text be ye further perſwaded from this Spectacle of Mortality now before you, <hi>viz.</hi> That of a ſtrong and luſty Young Man cut off in the midſt of his days, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was ſeiz'd with his Diſtemper, was as likely to live as any of you all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> As to the Life and Converſation of the Deceaſed, 'tis too well known already, and therefore I ſhall not meddle with it; but with reſpect to what was moſt remarkable in his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I think my ſelf obliged to take notice of, and adviſe theſe two things,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That you would Repent of and avoid thoſe ſins, which in his ſickneſs he publickly own'd himſelf guilty of, and profeſt to be ſorry for; and what they were, I ſuppoſe is well known to many here, ſpecially to ſuch as were his uſual Companions and Aſſociates.</p>
            <p>And therefore to ſuch as you, I ſhall more particularly apply my ſelf in this Diſcourſe, for whoſe Sakes it was chiefly deſign'd at firſt.</p>
            <p>Many great Sins and wilful neglects with reſpect to God and Religion, he openly lamented and bewailed, during his long and tedious Sickneſs, which yet ſeveral others among you are taken
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41585:14"/>Notice to be guilty of, as well as he, and therefore you have as much reaſon to repent of them, as he had, and if you do it not now, you may do it hereafter with leſs hopes and to leſs purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Remember thoſe Sins that troubled him, when Sick and Dying ought to trouble you that are now alive and in Health; thoſe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects of Religion and omiſſions of Duty, which ſate ſo heavy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Soul, may fit heavy on yours, and will do ſo too, when once God comes to ſet thoſe things home upon your Spirits, and to awaken your Conſciences by Sickneſs, Death, or any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Affliction.</p>
            <p>How light ſoever you may make of Sin now, the weight of it will be intolerable then, and without timely Repentance and amendment ſink you down to the bottomleſs Pit of Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The Remembrance of a wicked and ill ſpent Life, will fill you with Horror and Amazement, when God ſhall come to write <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things</hi> againſt you, and make you to <hi>poſſeſs your former Iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Spirit of a Man may hear his Infirmities,</hi> but a wounded Spirit who can bear? <hi>Prov.</hi> 'Tis poſſible we may be enabled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral accounts, to bear up under the one, whereas nothing will be able to ſupport us under the other; but Alas! When the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſhall be wounded with Guilt, and the Body at the ſame time weak and languiſhing with Pains and Sickneſs, how will it be poſſible then to bear up under both? When God at ſuch a time ſhall frown and look Angry, threaten and hide his Face, <hi>who then can abide,</hi> who will be able to ſpeak Peace; this can be no other than the Gate of Hell, and the beginning of its Torments.</p>
            <p>Let the deceaſed be a Warning and Example to you, God was pleas'd to puniſh him by a long and lingring Sickneſs, by a faint, reſtleſs, and uneaſie Diſtemper; none of us can tell what he ſuffer'd and endur'd all that while, but then at the ſame time his Soul was fill'd with Grief and Trouble, with Sorrow and Remorſe in the Remembrance of his Sins paſt, (and better ſo than otherwiſe, better be troubled for Sin, than go out of the World ſtupid and hardned without any Senſe thereof) and after all cut off in the midſt of his days, by a ſevere, yet righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41585:14"/>Diſpenſation of the Divine Providence, and how far God hath <hi>accepted his Sighs and Tears,</hi> we do not know, for ſecret things belong to God, therefore to God we muſt leave him; our Buſineſs is not to judge preremptorily concerning the <hi>Dead,</hi> but to warn and caution the <hi>Living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember therefore there is none of you all, how brisk and gay ſoever you may be in your Humors, how Confident and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure at preſent in your Sins, how ſtubborn and hardned againſt Reproof, but Sickneſs and Death will be able to tame and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, to pull down the Pride and Confidence of your Spirits. and fill you with Anguiſh and Bitterneſs of Soul in the thoughts of what you have deſerv'd, and therefore may juſtly expect and Fear.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Do not delay your Repentance to Sickneſs or Death, as he did, becauſe that is as you have heard, the moſt unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and inconvenient time to ſet about it. The deceaſed found it ſo, and did in effect acknowledge as much, when he wiſht he might live his Life over again, that he might ſpend and imploy it better.</p>
            <p>Now what God hath deny'd him, he hath in a great meaſure granted you; all of you at preſent are well in Health, and alive before God this Day, but how long you may continue ſo, none can tell. You know not how ſoon God may lay his Hand upon you by Death or Sickneſs, and cut off the Thread of your Lives unexpectedly to what you now hope for; and if your Repentance is not begun before that time, I fear you will be very unfit to ſet about it then.</p>
            <p>Alas, if Repentance is neceſſary when we are Sick or Dying, then it is neceſſary now, 'tis neceſſary every Hour and Moment of our Lives, becauſe we are Dying daily, and we know not how ſoon the Fatal ſtroke may be given, we are daily haſtning to the Grave, and we know not how ſoon our Feet may <hi>ſtumble on the dark Mountains,</hi> and if 'tis neceſſary to repent before we dye, then it is the wiſeſt courſe we can take to ſet about it in time, while God doth continue to us Life and Health, which is the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41585:15"/>fitteſt Opportunity for its performance, and if once loſt or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſlip from us, may never return more, we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meet with the like again, and then it will be in vain to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal miſpent time, or wiſh we might live our Lives over again, for time paſt can never be recall'd, the loſs of it will be irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable; all that we can do then is to bewail that which we can never repair, and to lament our Folly when 'twill be too late to grow wiſer by it.</p>
            <p>If you will not learn and take warning by the Example of the Deceas'd, you know not how ſoon God may make you a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Example to others, reduce you into as bad or worſe Circumſtances than he was in, and be forc'd to acknowledge the Juſtice of God in all that befall you, as he did.</p>
            <p>You have often ſeen and heard, how the Judgments of God have overtaken, both afar of and nearer hand, many bold and daring Offenders, ſinners every whit as Confident and Preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as any of you now preſent, and made them Examples of his juſt Anger and Diſpleaſure againſt ſin; and why then ſhould you think to eſcape more than they? Tho' you are not Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſht yet, doth it therefore follow you <hi>never</hi> ſhall? Is not the ſame Great and Holy God able to puniſh you, as he hath done them and many others; and hath he not threatned to do it too? Why than ſhould you think your ſelves more ſafe and ſecure from danger then they were, as long as you take ſo little care to prevent and avoid it?</p>
            <p>Go too, therefore, <hi>ye hardned and impenitent Wretches,</hi> ye mockers and deriders of all that is good and ſerious, ye that are apt to tempt and encourage one another in an evil way; take heed you do not provoke God to make you the next inſtance of his fierce Anger and Indignation; take heed you do not draw down the Wrath and Vengeance of Heaven upon your heads, and that ſooner than now you think for. For truth it ſelf hath told us, <hi>that great Plagues remain for the ungodly,</hi> Pſal. 32.10. That <hi>to God the Lord belong the iſſues of Death; but God will wound the head of his Enemies, and the hairy ſcalp of ſuch a one as goes on ſtill
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41585:15"/>in his Wickedneſs.</hi> Pſal. 68.20, 21. <hi>When they ſhall ſay Peace and Safety, then ſudden Deſtruction ſhall come upon them, as Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon a Woman with Child, and they ſhall not eſcape,</hi> 1. Theſ. 5.3. But <hi>he that being often reprov'd doth harden his neck, ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be deſtroy'd and that without Remedy,</hi> Prov. 29.1.</p>
            <p>After all this, can ye imagine, that the Patience of God, which hitherto hath been ſo forbearing and long-ſuffering, will always wait in vain, and ſuffer his goodneſs to be continually affronted and deſpiſed by the vileſt of his Creatures? No reaſon to think that Obſtinacy and Impenitency ſhall always go unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht; for you have but <hi>your</hi> time, and others have had <hi>theirs</hi> before you, who now reap the fruit of their Folly, and find to their Grief and Sorrow, what an <hi>evil and bitter thing it is, for to ſin againſt God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſuppoſe puniſhment ſhould be delay'd and no remarkable Judgment ſhould overtake you in this life; but you die in as ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid and ſecure a manner, as now you live: Yet the leſs you are puniſht here, the more reaſon you have to fear that God doth but reſerve you for greater puniſhment and vengeance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. For <hi>the Lord knows how to deliver the Godly out of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; but to reſerve the wicked to the day of Judgment to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.9. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf, yea even the wicked for the day of Evil,</hi> Prov. 16.4. And again, <hi>the wicked is reſerv'd to the day of Deſtruction; they ſhall be brought forth to the day of Wrath.</hi> Job, 21.30.</p>
            <p>Therefore, Sirs, think often of theſe things, and weigh them well in your Minds, for as <hi>Moſes</hi> told the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> it is for your Life, for the Life of your precious and immortal Souls, which are in danger to be loſt, and the loſs ſo great as can never be recompenc'd by a whole Life of Sin and Pleaſure, much leſs by thoſe Pleaſures, that laſt but <hi>for a moment,</hi> and die away in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them. I ſhall conclude all with thoſe Remarkable words of the Son of <hi>Sirach,</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Follow not thine own Mind, and thy Strength to walk in the ways of thy Heart.</q>
               <q>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41585:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Say not, who ſhall controul me for my Works? for the Lord will ſurely revenge thy Pride.</q>
               <q>Say not his Mercy is great, he will be pacify'd for the multitude of my Sins, for Mercy and Wrath come from him, and his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reſteth upon Sinners.</q>
               <q>Make no tarrying to turn unto the Lord, and put not off from day to day; for ſuddenly ſhall the wrath of the Lord come forth, and in thy Security thou ſhalt be deſtroyed, and Periſh in the day of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, <bibl>Eccleſ. 5.2, 3, 6, 7.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>Conſider this all ye that forget God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver, <bibl>Pſalm 50.22.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41585:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:41585:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
